Chapter 33. The specs cinder.
Concerning the officers of the whalecraft, this seems as good a place
as any to set down a little domestic peculiarity on shipboard, arising from
the existence of the harpooner class of officers, a class unknown, of course, in
any other marine than the whale fleet.
The large importance attached to the harpooner's vocation is evinced by the
fact that originally in the old Dutch fishery two centuries or more ago, the
command of a whale ship was not wholly lodged in the person now called the
captain, but was divided between him and an officer called the specsinder.
Literally, this word means fat cutter.
Usage, however, in time made it equivalent to chief harpooner. In those
days, the captain's authority was restricted to the navigation and general
management of the vessel, while over the whale hunting department and all its
concerns, the specs cinder or chief harpooner reigns supreme. In the British
Greenland fishery, under the corrupted title of specioner, this old Dutch
official is still retained, but his former dignity is sadly abridged. At
present he ranks simply as senior harpooner and as such is but one of the
captain's more inferior sub altern.
Nevertheless, as upon good conduct of the harpooners the success of a whailing
voyage largely depends, and since in the American fishery he is not only an
important officer in the boat, but under certain circumstances, night watches on
a whailing ground, the command of the ship's deck is also his. Therefore, the
grand political maxim of the sea demands that he should nominally live apart from
the men before the mast and be in some way distinguished as their professional
superior, though always by them familiarly regarded as their social equal.
Now, the grand distinction drawn between officer and man at sea is this. The
first lives aft, the last forward.
Hence, in whale ships and merchantmen alike, the mates have their quarters
with the captain, and so too in most of the American whalers, the harpooners are
lodged in the afterpart of the ship.
That is to say, they take their meals in the captain's cabin and sleep in a place
indirectly communicating with it.
Though the long period of a southern whailing voyage, by far the longest of
all voyages now or ever made by man, the peculiar perils of it, and the community
of interest prevailing among a company, all of whom, high or low, depend for
their profits, not upon fixed wages, but upon their common luck, together with
their common vigilance, intrepidity, and hard work. Though all these things do in
some cases tend to be get a less rigorous discipline than in merchant men
generally. Yet never mind how much like an old Mesopotamian family these
whalemen may in some primitive instances live together. For all that the
punctilious externals at least of the quarter deck are seldom materially
relaxed and in no instance done away.
Indeed, many are the Nantucket ships in which you will see the skipper parading
his quarter deck with an elated grandeur not surpassed in any military navy. Nay,
extorting almost as much outward homage as if he wore the imperial purple, not
the shabiest of pilot cloth.
And though of all men the moody captain of the Peekquad was the least given to
that sort of shallowest assumption, and though the only homage he ever exacted
was implicit instantaneous obedience, though he required no man to remove the
shoes from his feet stepping upon the quarter deck, and though there were
times when, owing to peculiar circumstances connected with events
hereafter to be detailed, he addressed them in unusual terms, whether of
condescension or in terorum or otherwise. Yet even Captain Ahab was by
no means unobservant of the paramount forms and usages of the sea. Nor perhaps
will it fail to be eventually perceived that behind those forms and usages, as
it were, he sometimes masked himself, incidentally making use of them for
other and more private ends than they were legitimately intended to subserve.
that certain sultanism of his brain which had otherwise in good degree remained unmanifested.
Through those forms that same sultanism became incarnate in an irresistible dictatorship.
For be a man's intellectual superiority what it will. It can never assume the
practical available supremacy over other men without the aid of some sort of
external arts and entrenchments always in themselves more or less poultry in
base. This it is that forever keeps God's true princes of the empire from
the world's hustings, and leaves the highest honors that this heir can give
to those men who become famous more through their infinite inferiority to
the choice hidden handful of the divine inert than through their undoubted
superiority over the dead level of the mass. Such large virtue lurks in these
small things, when extreme political superstitions invest them, that in some
royal instances, even to idiot imbecelity, they have imparted potency.
But when, as in the case of Nicholas Thesar, the ringed crown of geographical
empire encircles an imperial brain, then the plebeian herds crouch a based before
the tremendous centralization.
Nor will the tragic dramatist who would depict moral indomitableness in its
fullest sweep and direct swing ever forget a hint incidentally so important
in his art as the one now alluded to.
But Ahab, my captain, still moves before me in all his Nantucket grimness and
shaggginess, and in this episode touching emperors and kings, I must not
conceal that I have only to do with a poor old whale hunter like him, and
therefore all outward majestical trappings and housings are denied me. Oh
Ahab, what shall be grand in thee, it must needs be plucked at from the skies
and dived for in the deep and featured in the unbodied air.